<html>
    <!-- This is a truncated HTML file, used only for grabbing content out of the body tag -->
    
    <body>
        
        <h2>Browse</h2>
    

        <h3>
            The Letters
        </h3>
        
        <div class="lineup_three smaller">
            <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.BROWSEImage2.penpaper.jpg" class="left"></img>
            <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.BROWSEImage1Study.jpg" class="center"></img>
            <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.BROWSEImage3Typewrtr.jpg" class="right"></img>
        </div>
        
        
        <p>
            [Image 2 / Image 1 / Image 3(left to right) Photo credits: Christian Wilson]
        </p>
        <p>
            This archive will contain the correspondence of John G. Neihardt (1881-1973) divided into two important categories: 1)    <strong><em>Collected Professional and Literary Letters </em></strong>and 2) <strong><em>Personal and Family Correspondence</em></strong>.
        </p>
        <p>
            Copies of many of Neihardt’s out-going professional and literary letters were collected by his biographer, Lucile Aly. Comprised of approximately 1,204
            letters that date from as early as 1905 through September, 1973, these files are currently housed in the Neihardt Center in Bancroft, NE. The “Aly
            Collection” also includes approximately 1,385 letters written to Neihardt during the same time period. In addition, the Center holds over 850 original
            family letters, some written by or to Neihardt, while others were exchanged between other family members.
        </p>
        <p>
            The originals of these copies and other original letters by Neihardt are scattered across the country in various archives and libraries such as the
            University of Missouri, the New York Public Library, the Huntington Library, and Dartmouth Library. Others are in private hands.
        </p>
        <p>
            Our first goal here will be to digitize, encode and make accessible and searchable the text of those copies of letters that Neihardt himself composed. We
            will then undertake a world-wide search to gather all of his extant letters, both outgoing and incoming. Many of the earliest letters in the Aly Collection
            present distinct challenges to the digitalization and encoding processes as they are primarily hand-written, often contain script on both sides of the
            paper, and frequently include writing that moves in more than one direction across the page. Later letters are more typically typewritten, although they
            often contain handwritten notes as well.
        </p>
        <p>
            Among the outgoing correspondence in the Aly Collection, we find letters that Neihardt wrote to the literary editors of various journals and presses, and
            the editors of newspapers he worked for (e.g. the <em>Minneapolis Journal</em>, <em>Kansas City Journal Post</em>, Joseph Pulitzer at the    <em>St. Louis Post-Dispatch</em>), as well as to other writers, such as George Sterling, Upton Sinclair and Mari Sandoz. Through his letters to close
            confidantes and friends, including Nicholas and Ben Black Elk, we can trace the evolution of his various essays and short stories and his longer works,    <em>Black Elk Speaks</em> and <em>A Cycle of the West</em>. We can also observe the trajectory of Neihardt’s growing literary and intellectual reputation
            through his letters to public figures such as then-Colonel Theodore Roosevelt and President Harry S. Truman and through the numerous honors and awards he
            received from state and regional organizations and national literary societies (as well as his “row” with <em>Poetry Magazine</em> and his near-misses with
            the Pulitzer—twice). Many letters provide information and insights into his joyfully chaotic family life, including their many moves from Bancroft to
            Minneapolis, to Branson, St. Louis and beyond. Others offer details of Neihardt’s extensive and adventurous research-trips down the Missouri River and
            along the central portion of the Oregon Trail. His “outgoing” letters were sent as close to home as the Black Hills in South Dakota and as far away as New
            Delhi, India.
        </p>
        <p>
            The incoming letters held at the Neihardt Center are equally diverse, dating from the fall of 1900 to late 1973. They include correspondence with writers,
            critics and thinkers of national stature, such as Jessie B. Rittenhouse, H. L. Mencken, Louis Untermeyer, Sinclair, Pulitzer, Carl Sandberg, Carl Van
            Doren, and J. E. Boodin, as well as a number of writers with close Nebraska ties, e.g. Mildred Bennett, Nellie Yost, Marion Marsh Brown and Sandoz.
        </p>
        <h3>
            Essays and Reviews
        </h3>
        
        
        
        
        <p>
            <div class="left smaller">
                <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.BROWSEImage4studyintr.jpg"></img>
                <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.BROWSEImage5NinBranLibNC.jpg"></img>
            </div>
            
            This archive will contain examples of the myriad essays and reviews that Neihardt wrote over his long career as a literary book review editor, cultural
            critic and social observer.
        <br/><br/>
            
            While Lori Holm Utecht’s invaluable <em>Knowledge and Opinon: Essays and Literary Criticism of John G. Neihardt</em> (University of Nebraska Press, 2002)
            offers an insightfully representative sample of these materials (approximately 118 essays), Neihardt wrote a staggering number of
            such works, perhaps as many as 3,000 total. The materials that we gather here are intended to complement and extend the themes and topics covered in
            Utecht’s volume and serve as a friendly companion to them.
        </p>
        <p>
            [Image 4: Photo credit: Christian Wilson / Image 5: JGNHS?/Neihardt Trust?, permission pending]
        </p>
        <p>
            Through the “short forms” of the essay and review, Neihardt directly and seriously engaged an amazing array of cultural, historical, social, political,
            philosophical, aesthetic, spiritual and scientific ideas and debates. Regularly reading and reviewing at the rate of one book per day (occasionally more!),
            he took on subjects that ranged from ancient civilizations to atomic theory and emergent astrophysics (Einstein, Eddington, Jeans), human nature and
            psychology (Freud, behaviorism) to evolutionary theories and social Darwinism (Darwin, Wallace, Spencer, Malthus), as well as new technological
            developments and possibilities (from telegraphs to rocketry).
        </p>
        <p>
            Collectively, these materials provide new interpretative frameworks and insights into the sophistication and scope of Neihardt’s intellectual interests,
            aesthetic philosophy, literary work, professional and personal relationships and life itself, the medium in which he most sought to create a grand
            synthesis of thought and action, the ideal and the real.
        </p>
        <p>
            By making readily available as many examples of Neihardt’s correspondence, critical essays and reviews as possible, we hope that this archive will provide
            fresh content and new contexts for past and current scholarly analyses of Neihardt’s life and work. Through these materials, both new readers and those
            long-devoted to Neihardt’s creative literary works should discover much information previously unknown to them and many surprising interconnections that
            will enrich their understanding of his many “voices and visions.”
        </p>
        <p>
            As these collections of letters and essays clearly evidence, whether reading and writing in small-town Nebraska or Missouri, the burgeoning cities of
            Minneapolis or St. Louis, Neihardt traveled far afield, physically, intellectually and philosophically.
        </p>
        <div class="lineup_three smaller">
            <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.BROWSEImage6roadout.jpg" class="left"></img>
            <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.BROWSEImage7cornrows.jpg" class="center"></img>
            <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.BROWSEImage8JGNonroadNC.jpg" class="right"></img>
        </div>
        
        
        <p>
            [left to right: image 6 / image 8 / image 7; Photo Credits for 6 &amp; 7: Christian Wilson; Image 8: JGNHS? / Neihardt Trust? Permission pending]
        </p>
        <p>
            PHOTO LIST / CAPTIONS (if needed):
        </p>
        <p>
            Image 1: Neihardt’s restored study at John G. Neihardt State Historic Site, Bancroft NE
        </p>
        <p>
            Image 2: Neihardt’s desktop at the John G. Neihardt State Historic Site, Bancroft, NE
        </p>
        <p>
            Image 3: Typewriter in the study at the John G. Neihardt State Historic Site, Bancroft, NE
        </p>
        <p>
            Image 4: Interior of study at John G. Neihardt State Historic Site, Bancroft, NE
        </p>
        <p>
            Image 5: Neihardt in his library in Branson [placeholder, pending permission request]
        </p>
        <p>
            Image 6: Road outside Bancroft, NE
        </p>
        <p>
            Image 7: Cornrows outside Bancroft, NE
        </p>
        <p>
            Image 8: Neihardt on road outside Bancroft, NE [placeholder, pending permission request]
        </p>


    </body>

</html>
