<html>
    <!-- This is a truncated HTML file, used only for grabbing content out of the body tag -->
    
    <body>
        

<h2>Across the Spectrum:</h2>
<h3>The Interdisciplinary Life and Letters of John G. Neihardt</h3>
<p>Pamela Gossin</p>
 
 
        <div class="lineup_three smaller">
            <img src="files/figures/illustrations/large/JGNHOMEDSC_7271.jpg" class="left"></img>
            <img src="files/figures/illustrations/large/JGNHOMEDSC_6764.jpg" class="center"></img>
            <img src="files/figures/illustrations/large/jgn_in_study.jpg" class="right"></img>
        </div>
        
       
        <p>
            <strong><em>Across the Spectrum: The Interdisciplinary Life and Letters of John G. Neihardt</em></strong>
            represents two of the five major components of <strong>The Neihardt Projects</strong>. Project 1 provides an extensive searchable digital archive of
            Neihardt’s collected professional and personal letters. Project 2 is an interpretative website that serves as a contextual framework for the digital
            archive of correspondence and provides users with digitized texts of previously uncollected essays and reviews as well as a variety of useful research aids
            and scholarly perspectives.
        </p>
        <p>
            When complete, the archive of Neihardt’s <strong><em>Collected Professional and Literary Letters </em></strong>and    <strong><em>Personal and Family Correspondence</em></strong> will contain the equivalent of more than 15 standard print volumes and the website will
            include transcriptions of hundreds of his literary essays and book reviews.
        </p>
        <p>
            Both the archive and website are currently under construction in cooperation with and with the support of the Plains Humanities Alliance, the Center for
            Great Plains Studies and the Center for Research in the Digital Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln.
        </p>
        <p>
            ~ ~ ~
        </p>
        <p>
            <strong>The Neihardt Projects </strong>
            also include three additional components. Project 3 focuses on the production of two new traditional print book volumes:<strong><em>Neihardt on Science: Selected Essays and Reviews 1913 - 1938</em></strong> and    <strong><em>Voices and Visions: Selected Letters of John G. Neihardt</em></strong>. <strong><em>Neihardt on Science</em></strong> will bring together in
            one place, for the first time, a selection of over 200 of Neihardt’s science essays and book reviews on such topics as ecology, evolutionary theory,
            astronomy, Einsteinian physics, sociology, psychology, ESP, mysticism and futurism. In <strong><em>Voices and Visions</em></strong>, the selected letters
            will offer a sampling of the range of new insights made available by the digital archive’s collected correspondence regarding Neihardt’s aesthetic
            philosophy, literary work, professional and personal relationships and home life. Together with the archive and website, we hope that these materials will
            enrich understanding of Neihardt’s life and works for scholars and general readers for many decades to come. Both print projects
            have been reviewed and approved by the Neihardt Trust.
        </p>
        <p>
            Projects 4 and 5 are slated for development over the next 7-8 years. Project 4 will develop educational outreach materials, including the creation and
            distribution of an interdisciplinary K-12 curriculum with related children’s exhibits. These materials will offer educators downloadable interdisciplinary
            instructional content (pdfs, podcasts, video and music files) developed to Nebraska State Department of Education standards for use in Language Arts,
            History, Social Studies, Art and Music. Some of these materials will form the basis of portable exhibits for use by schools, libraries, Scout troops, civic
            groups and American Indian organizations. Project 5 will involve the archival preservation and conservation of original documents and materials, through
            both digitalization and traditional methods.
        </p>







    </body></html>