<html>
    <!-- This is a truncated HTML file, used only for grabbing content out of the body tag -->

    <body>

        <h2>About</h2>



        <h3>Purpose and History</h3>
        <p>
            <em>Across the Spectrum: The Interdisciplinary Life and Letters of John G. Neihardt</em>
            is a scholarly digital archive and research website that provides two key components of
            The Neihardt Projects. </p>
        
        <div class="center smaller">
        <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.ABOUTImage1.NeihCenter.jpg"></img>
        <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.ABOUTImage2.Garden.jpg"></img>
        </div>

        <p> Since 1976, the museum, library, and prayer garden of the Neihardt Center in Bancroft,
            NE have served as the spiritual heart of Neihardt studies, offering educational and
            commemorative events to the state and region year round. The five central components of
            The Neihardt Projects are intended to radiate out from this Center, expanding the
            influence of Neihardt’s works and ideas by bringing them fully onto the global stage
            through the use of new media and digital humanities. The central aim of The Neihardt
            Projects is to “un-hide” what have long been regarded as the hidden treasures of
            Neihardt’s contributions to the literature, culture and history of the American Great
            Plains, making his works and ideas more fully accessible to 21<sup>st</sup> -century
            readers and scholars around the world. [Image 1, 2, 3, Photo Credits: Christian Wilson] </p>
        <div class="center smaller">
            <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.ABOUTImage3RedBlkRoad.jpg"></img>

        </div>
        <p> The efforts of The Neihardt Projects will supplement and complement long-established and
            highly successful programs of publication and education in Neihardt studies by many
            other committed individuals and organizations, such as the University of Nebraska Press,
            SUNY Press, the Neihardt Foundation and the Nebraska State Historical Society. Emphasis
            throughout all aspects of the Projects will be on working cooperatively with existing
            enterprises to create new bridges between academic communities and the general public,
            across generations and across cultures, following as empathetically as possible in
            Neihardt’s own diverse interdisciplinary footsteps and extending his mission to
            “translate and transmit” his poetic vision and wide-ranging thought and experiences. </p>
        
        
        
        
        <p><div class="left smaller icons">
            <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.ABOUTImage4and5.jpg"></img>
        </div>
        While many of Neihardt’s creative works have long been in print (<strong><em>Black
                    Elk Speaks</em></strong>,<strong><em> Cycle of the West</em></strong> etc), he
            also wrote over 2,000 professional and personal letters and nearly 3,000 critical essays
            and reviews. Scattered in archives across the country, copies of many of these
            materials— and some originals—are housed in the Neihardt Center. Utilized by a small,
            but steady, stream of scholars over the years, these documents have never been widely
            accessible or searchable, yet collectively they offer transformative new perspectives on
            Neihardt’s life and times. </p>
        <p> [Images 4 and 5 Photo credit: Christian Wilson] </p>
        <p> From his supposedly isolated rural surroundings, Neihardt created and maintained an
            active intellectual engagement in scientific and technological developments and world
            affairs, sharing his take on “western civilization” with the growing population of the
            Louisiana Purchase. In close cooperation with the Neihardt Center, the Neihardt
            Foundation, the Neihardt Trust, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities,
            Plains Humanities Alliance and Center for Great Plains Studies at UNL, the Neihardt
            Projects’ website, digital archive, print volumes and educational outreach will extend
            and connect Neihardt’s readership, so that more people worldwide will have access to
            Neihardt’s creative model for interdisciplinary and cross-cultural ways of thinking and
            being. </p>
        <h3> Acknowledgements</h3>
        <p> Inspiration for The Neihardt Projects first began with a serendipitous conversation in
            the summer of 2008 with Nancy Gillis, Executive Director of the Neihardt Center. Early
            seeds of possibilities grew into ambitious plans with the further insights and
            imaginative support of Coralie Hughes and Robin Neihardt (grandchildren of John G.) and
            the Neihardt Trust (which reviewed and approved the full proposal for The Projects).
            Everyone at the Neihardt Center and Neihardt Trust has been unfailingly helpful and
            encouraging, with special “above and beyond” thanks to Nancy and her staff assistants,
            Mary Petersen and Norma Farrens, and maintenance staff, Rod Peters, all of whom braved
            record-setting snowfall – with 8-foot drifts up to the eaves of the Center – to enable
            us to begin work on the Projects over Christmas break 2009. </p>
        <p> The initial construction of the Neihardt digital archive and website has been supported
            by a Plains Humanities Alliance Fellowship in Digital Humanities for 2011-13 and through
            a Pollock-Dudley Research Award from the Dudley Observatory, Schnectady, NY. Together
            these funds have supported research into the range and extent of Neihardt’s science
            writing and the scanning of over 9,000 images of original letters and photographs (so
            far) during the summers of 2010, 2011 and 2012. </p>
        <p> A serious – and still accumulating – debt of gratitude is due to everyone at the Center
            for Digital Research in the Humanities, especially Co-Director, Dr. Katherine Walter,
            Digital Resources Designer, Karin Daziel and Metadata Encoding Specialist, Laura Weakley
            who have all so generously shared their expertise, encouragement and patient teaching
            (and re-teaching) with the Project Director and Staff who have definitely been climbing
            a “steep learning curve.” Thank you too to [names of CDRH student workers] who have
            transcribed and coded the earliest handwritten letters. It has been immensely and
            immeasurably beneficial to have The Neihardt Projects welcomed into a scholarly and
            educational community where everyone is so dedicated to working cooperatively to make
            the potential actual and in so many effective ways. </p>
        <p> The Neihardt Projects are also grateful to the School of Arts and Humanities at the
            University of Texas at Dallas which recently designated a small office in the Jonsson
            Building as dedicated “Digital Humanities Workspace,” providing office furnishings and
            several computer workstations. This workspace–shared with Dr. Jessica Murphy and the
            English Broadside Ballad Archive—will enable the directors of these two projects to
            train and consult with graduate and undergraduate research assistants and provide
            on-campus collaborative workspace for both research assistants and future DH interns.
            Both Drs. Gossin and Murphy are involved in the new and growing DFW-Area Digital
            Humanities Colloquium which aims to develop a community of DH scholars in North Texas. </p>
        <h3> Project Staff</h3>
        <h4>Project Director: </h4>
        
        
        
        
        

        <p>
            
            <div class="left smaller gossin">
            <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.ABOUTImage6PSG1.jpg"></img>
            <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.ABOUTImage7PSG2.jpg"></img>
            <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.ABOUTImage8PSG3.jpg"></img>
        </div>
        
            <strong>Pamela Gossin</strong> is Professor of History of Science and Literary Studies
            and Affiliate Professor of Science Education at the University of Texas at Dallas where
            she directs the Medical and Scientific Humanities (MaSH) program. A “Husker Girl” at
            heart, she was born and raised in Lincoln and owns and operates her grandparents’
            farmstead near Cairo, NE. A graduate of the University of Nebraska-Lincoln (BA in
            English and Latin with a Math minor; MA in English, with a concentration in British and
            American Literature, especially Great Plains Studies), she served as Curator of the
            Nebraska History and Literature Collections in the Heritage Room of the Lincoln Public
            Libraries before completing a double-PhD in the History of Science and English at the
            University of Wisconsin. Her publications include a book chapter, “Lessons of an
            Interdisciplinary Life: Loren Eiseley’s Rhetoric of Profundity and the ‘Two Cultures’
            Classroom” for<em>Artifacts and Illuminations: Critical Essays on Loren Eiseley</em>,
            eds. Susan Maher and Tom Lynch (University of Nebraska Press, 2012),<em> Thomas Hardy’s
                Novel Universe: Astronomy, Cosmology and Gender in the Post-Darwinian World</em>
            (Ashgate) and <em>An Encyclopedia of Literature and Science</em> (Greenwood) which
            includes entries on Nebraska authors Weldon Kees and Eiseley. With the approval of the
            Neihardt Trust, she is currently working on two interrelated book
                    projects:<strong><em>Neihardt on Science: Selected Essays and Reviews, 1913 –
                    1938 </em></strong>and <strong><em>Visions and Voices: Selected Letters of John
                    G. Neihardt</em></strong>.<em></em>
        </p>
        <h4>Bancroft Research Assistants:</h4>
        
        
        
        <p>
            
            <div class="left smaller">
            <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.ABOUTImage9EJ.jpg"></img>
        </div>
            
            <strong>Eric Johnson</strong> – a native of Blair, Nebraska, is currently a senior at
            Northwestern University, Evanston IL, working toward a major in Anthropology with a
            double minor in Latin and Music Composition. As an undergraduate RA for The Neihardt
            Projects during the summers of 2011 and 2012, he set up the organizational framework and
            databases for the digitalization and scanned over 6,000 images of Neihardt’s
            professional correspondence held in the Neihardt Center. Having completed archaeological
            fieldwork in southeast England, he will soon be pursuing a graduate degree in
            archaeology. [Image 9 Photo Credit: Christian Wilson] </p>
        
        
            
        
            <p><div class="left smaller">
                <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.ABOUTImage10.jpg"></img>
            </div><strong>Christian Wilson </strong> – is a<strong> </strong>senior in the Medill School
            of Journalism at Northwestern, where his studies focus on photojournalism. During the
            summer of 2012, he scanned hundreds of images of correspondence and also took hundreds
            of original photographs in and around Bancroft and the Neihardt historical site,
            including many that have been incorporated into this website. Christian has held
            positions as a photojournalism intern at the <em>Pacific Northwest Inlander</em>
            magazine, Spokane, WA, the <em>Daily Herald</em> newspaper, Arlington Heights, IL, and
                <em>The Oklahoman</em>, Oklahoma City, OK. His favorite moment as a journalist:
            receiving his press pass to UNL’s Memorial Stadium to shoot NU vs. NU in the Fall of
            2011 for the <em>Daily Northwestern </em>(a special challenge in journalistic integrity,
            since he’s a Husker fan).<em> </em>More of his work can be seen at:
            christianwilsonphotography.tumblr.com. [ Image 10 Photo Credit: ]<em></em>
        </p>
        <p>
            <u>UT-Dallas Research Assistants:</u>
        </p>
        <p>
            <div class="left smaller">
                <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.ABOUTImage11Gavran.jpg"></img>
            </div>
            <strong>Julie Gavran</strong> – is a PhD candidate in the School of Arts and Humanities
            at the University of Texas at Dallas where she is researching the life and work of
            Benton MacKaye, the founder of the Appalachian Trail. Neihardt corresponded with
            MacKaye’s brother, Percy, and one of her first “finds” was an original letter from
            Neihardt to Percy in the Dartmouth Library. During the fall 2012 and spring 2013, she
            has been transcribing examples of Neihardt’s science writing from his early newspaper
            days in the first decades of the 20<sup>th</sup> century. She also serves as regional
            coordinator for the Campaign to Keep Guns Off Campus. This national organization works
            with university leaders, faculty and students to block legislation that would force
            colleges and universities to allow firearms on campuses. [Image 11 Photo credit: Andrew
            Famiglietti] </p>
        <p>
            <u>SPECIAL THANKS: </u>
        </p>
        <p> The earliest stages of this project’s development benefitted greatly from the assistance
            of Victor Wilson and Will Gossin both of whom helped with the initial reconnaissance of
            the correspondence held in the Neihardt Center at Bancroft, provided expert technical
            support, organized materials, scanned indices and sample letters, and helped explore and
            inventory the treasure-trove we found there. </p>
        
        <div class="lineup_three smaller">
            <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.ABOUTImage14Farm.jpg" class="left"></img>
            <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.ABOUTImage12BancroftSign.jpg" class="center"></img>
            <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.ABOUTImage13Fields.jpg" class="right"></img>
        </div>
        
        
        
        <p> Thank you also to Paul and Don Hammel for providing appropriately rural, picturesque
            (and affordable!) housing for our summertime Research Assistants who thoroughly enjoyed
            exploring the hills and fields around Bancroft, the spectacular sunsets, and filling the
            farmhouse with the sound of their late-night folk guitar jams. [Photo credits: Christian
            Wilson] </p>
        
        <div class="lineup_two smaller">
            <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.ABOUTImage16CombineSun.jpg" class="left"></img>
            <img src="../files/figures/illustrations/large/JGN.ABOUTImage15BancroftFieldRd.jpg" class="right"></img>
        </div>
  
        <p> PHOTO LIST / CAPTIONS (if needed): </p>
        <p> Image 1: John G. Neihardt State Historic Site, Bancroft NE </p>
        <p> Image 2: Sacred Hoop Prayer Garden at Neihardt State Historic Site </p>
        <p> Image 3: stone marker in Sacred Hoop Prayer Garden, from <em>Black Elk Speaks</em>
        </p>
        <p> Image 4: cover of Black Elk Speaks </p>
        <p> Image 5: cover of Cycle of the West </p>
        <p> Image 6: cover of Artifact and Illuminations </p>
        <p> Image 7: cover of Thomas Hardy’s Novel Universe </p>
        <p> Image 8: cover of Encyclopedia of Lit and Sci </p>
        <p> Image 9: Eric Johnson </p>
        <p> Image 10: Christian Wilson </p>
        <p> Image 11: Julie Gavran </p>
        <p> Image 12: Bancroft, NE welcome sign </p>
        <p> Image 13: fields outside Bancroft, NE </p>
        <p> Image 14: farm outside Bancroft, NE </p>
        <p> Image 15: fields and road outside Bancroft, NE </p>
        <p> Image 16: combine at sunset, outside Bancroft, NE </p>





        <!-- 
    <p>Text about the site will go here, including credits.</p>
    
<ul>
        <li>Major Components
        <ul>
            <li>Website and Archive</li>
            <li>Print Volumes</li>
            <li>K-12 Curriculum</li>
            <li>Preservation and Conservation</li>
        </ul></li>
    </ul>-->
    </body>
</html>
