<html>
    <!-- This is a truncated HTML file, used only for grabbing content out of the body tag -->

    <body>
        <div class="lineup_three smaller">
            <!--         <img src="files/figures/illustrations/large/JGNHOMEDSC_7271.jpg" class="left"></img> -->
            <!--<img src="files/figures/illustrations/large/JGNHOMEDSC_6764.jpg" class="center"></img>-->
            <!--         <img src="files/figures/illustrations/large/jgn_in_study.jpg" class="right"></img> -->
        </div>
        <p>
            <strong><em>Across the Spectrum: The Interdisciplinary Life and Letters of John G.
                    Neihardt</em></strong> provides an extensive searchable digital archive of
            Neihardt’s collected professional and personal letters along with previously uncollected
            essays and reviews. Accompanying interpretative essays provide a contextual framework
            for the digital archive. When complete, the archive will contain the equivalent of more
            than 15 standard print volumes of Neihardt's original nonfiction prose writings. </p>
        <p> In conjunction with this archive, two new print volumes <strong><em>Neihardt on Science:
                    Selected Essays and Reviews 1913-1938</em></strong> and <strong><em>Voices and
                    Visions: Selected Letters of John G. Neihardt</em></strong> have been reviewed
            and approved by the Neihardt Trust. Both of these volumes have been invited for
            submission to the University of Nebraska Press. <strong><em>Neihardt on
                Science</em></strong> will bring together in one place, for the first time, a
            selection of over 200 of Neihardt’s science essays and book reviews on such topics as
            ecology, evolutionary theory, astronomy, Einsteinian physics, sociology, psychology,
            ESP, mysticism and futurism. In <strong><em>Voices and Visions</em></strong>, the
            selected letters will offer a sampling of the range of new insights made available by
            the digital archive’s collected correspondence regarding Neihardt’s aesthetic
            philosophy, literary work, professional and personal relationships and home life.
            Together with the archive and website, we hope that these materials will enrich
            understanding of Neihardt’s life and works for scholars and general readers for many
            decades to come. </p>
        <p>
            <strong><em>Across the Spectrum</em></strong> is a significant part of a long-term
            vision for <strong><em>The Neihardt Projects</em></strong> which - over the next 5-7
            years - will also include the development of educational outreach materials, the
            creation and distribution of an interdisciplinary K-12 curriculum, and related
            children’s exhibits. These materials will offer educators downloadable interdisciplinary
            instructional content (pdfs, podcasts, video and music files) developed to Nebraska
            State Department of Education standards for use in Language Arts, History, Social
            Studies, Art and Music. Some of these materials will form the basis of portable exhibits
            for use by schools, libraries, Scout troops, civic groups and American Indian
            organizations. </p>
        <p>
            <strong><em>Across the Spectrum</em></strong> is edited by Pamela Gossin, Professor of
            History of Science and Literary Studies and Affiliate Professor of Science Education at
            the University of Texas at Dallas. An Associate Fellow of the Center for Great Plains
            Studies, Professor Gossin also serves as the Director of <strong><em>The Neihardt
                    Projects</em></strong>. The archive is under construction in cooperation with
            and with the support of the Plains Humanities Alliance, the Center for Great Plains
            Studies and the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
            Nebraska-Lincoln. </p>
    </body>
</html>
