<html>
    <!-- This is a truncated HTML file, used only for grabbing content out of the body tag -->

    <body>
        <h2>Essays &amp; Reviews</h2>
        <p class="intro_description">This archive contains examples of the myriad essays and reviews
            that Neihardt wrote over his long career as a literary book review editor, cultural
            critic and social observer. Through the “short forms” of the essay and review, Neihardt
            directly and seriously engaged an amazing array of cultural, historical, social,
            political, philosophical, aesthetic, spiritual and scientific ideas and debates.
            Regularly reading and reviewing at the rate of one book per day (occasionally more!), he
            took on subjects that ranged from ancient civilizations to atomic theory and emergent
            astrophysics (Einstein, Eddington, Jeans), human nature and psychology (Freud,
            behaviorism) to evolutionary theories and social Darwinism (Darwin, Wallace, Spencer,
            Malthus), as well as new technological developments and possibilities (from telegraphs
            to rocketry).</p>
        <p>Collectively, these materials provide new interpretative frameworks and insights into the
            sophistication and scope of Neihardt’s intellectual interests, aesthetic philosophy,
            literary work, professional and personal relationships and life itself, the medium in
            which he most sought to create a grand synthesis of thought and action, the ideal and
            the real.</p>
        <span class="extended_description">
            <p>By making readily available as many examples of Neihardt’s correspondence, critical
                essays and reviews as possible, we hope that this archive will provide fresh content
                and new contexts for past and current scholarly analyses of Neihardt’s life and
                work. Through these materials, both new readers and those long-devoted to Neihardt’s
                creative literary works should discover much information previously unknown to them
                and many surprising interconnections that will enrich their understanding of his
                many “voices and visions.”</p>
            <p>As these collections of letters and essays clearly evidence, whether reading and
                writing in small-town Nebraska or Missouri, the burgeoning cities of Minneapolis or
                St. Louis, Neihardt traveled far afield, physically, intellectually and
                philosophically.</p>
        </span>
        <!-- <ul>
        <li><a href="narrative.html">Descriptive Narrative</a></li>
        <li><a href="mission.html">Mission Statement</a></li>
        <li><a href="biographical_sketches.html">Biographical Sketches</a></li>
        <li><a href="scholarly_perspectives.html">Scholarly Perspectives and Inspiration</a></li>
        <li><a href="mapping.html">Beyond "Regional": Mapping Connections and Contexts</a></li>
    </ul>
    -->
    </body>
</html>
